A Finding Aid to the Theodore F. Wolff Papers, 1920-2013, bulk 1977-2013, in the Archives of American Art AAA.wolftheo
Archives of American Art
Theodore F. Wolff papers
bulk 1977-2013
1920-2013
AAA.wolftheo
Archives of American Art
8 Linear feet
The papers of art critic, writer, and painter Theodore F. Wolff measure 8 linear feet and date from 1920-2013, with the bulk of the material dating from 1977-2013. The collection documents Wolff's career through biographical material, correspondence, interviews, writings, subject files, printed material, a small amount of artwork, and photographs.
Wolff, Theodore F.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of art critic, writer, and painter Theodore F. Wolff measure 8 linear feet and date from 1920-2013, with the bulk of the material dating from 1977-2013. The collection documents Wolff's career through biographical material, correspondence, interviews, writings, subject files, printed material, a small portion of artwork, and photographs.
Biographical material consists of biographical data, curriculum vitae, and awards. Included are outgoing and incoming letters that document Wolff's activities as an art critic, appraiser, and fine arts consultant. A large portion of his correspondence is with artists. Among the correspondents are Richard Diebenkorn, Alexander Hogue, Ynez Johnston, Armin Landeck, Melissa Miller, Robert Natkin, Theodoros Stamos, Athena Tachna, Jerome Witkin, and the writer Tom Wolfe. There is significant correspondence with Morris Graves, James Hubbell, Clyfford Still, and Stow Wengenroth relating to their work and Wolff's writings.
Interviews consist of three interviews with Theodore F. Wolff as well as a panel discussion with Wolff and other artists. Found are interviews with Enrico Donati and James Turrell. Recordings are on five sound cassettes and three videocassettes. Writings consist of Wolff's reviews, mostly tearsheets for The Christian Monitor and draft versions of a book. Also included are talks and lectures on art and art education recorded on seven videocassettes and six sound cassettes. Subject files document Wolff's professional interests and relate to his writing projects, exhibitions, talks, and presentations. Included are interviews with artists that were used by Theodore Wolff as source material.
Printed material includes Theodore F. Wolff's published critical writings on art, artists, and education. Included are exhibition catalogs, brochures, journals, and monographs. Artwork consists of seventeen sketches by Wolff done early in his career. Photographs are of Theodore F. Wolff and with friends and colleagues, many of them unidentified. Included are photographs of Wolff with Ida Kohlmeyer.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
A small amount of material was donated in 1999 by Theodore F. Wolff. Additional papers were donated in 2013 by Collette Wolff, widow of Theodore F. Wolff.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
Theodore F. Wolff (1926-2012) was an art critic, writer, and painter in New York City.
Wolff attended the University of Wisconsin, earning a Bachelor of Arts degree in Art Education in 1949 and a Masters degree in Art and Art History the following year. By the early 1950s, Wolff was living in San Francisco, where he began his professional career as a painter. In 1956, he and his wife, Collette Wolff, moved to New York. During this period, Wolff also worked as an art appraiser and fine arts consultant for collectors, galleries, and museums. In 1977, Wolff began writing art criticism for The Christian Science Monitor and held the post of art critic at the publication until 1990. In addition to his art columns to The Monitor, Wolff contributed critical and introductory essays on artists for exhibition catalogs and journals. Theodore F. Wolff taught and lectured on art and art education at museums, universities, and conferences. In 1982, he received the National Headliners Award for Consistently Outstanding Column on Art and the Art World Award for Distinguished Newspaper Art Criticism in 1983. In 1990, Theodore Wolff retired from The Christian Science Monitor. He devoted the latter part of his career to painting, writing, lecturing, and teaching.
Theodore F. Wolff died in 2012 in New York City. He is survived by his wife, Collette Wolff.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1982-2013 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1920, 1951-2011 (Box 1; 0.75 linear feet)
Series 3: Interviews, circa 1990-2002 (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, Talks, and Lectures, circa 1977-2005 (Boxes 2-4; 2.8 linear feet)
Series 5: Subject Files, circa 1940, 1964-2004 (Boxes 4-6; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1956-2006 (Boxes 6-8; 2.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, 1942-1948 (Box 7, 1 folder)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1980-circa 2011 (Box 7; 0.25 linear feet)
Diebenkorn, Richard, 1922-1993; Donati, Enrico, 1909-2008; Hogue, Alexandre, 1898-; Johnston, Ynez, 1920-; Kohlmeyer, Ida, 1912-1997; Landeck, Armin, 1905-; Miller, Melissa; Natkin, Robert, 1930-; Stamos, Theodoros, 1922-1997; Tacha, Athena, 1936-; Turrell, James; Witkin, Jerome; Art critics--New York (State)--New York; Art--Study and teaching; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Interviews; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Sketches; Sound recordings; Video recordings
- Biographical Material, 1982-2013; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains biographical data, curriculum vitae, and awards, including a plaque from Manufacturers Hanover Trust to Wolff for Distinguished Newspaper Art Criticism. Included is a handmade card to Theodore F. Wolff from his colleagues, presumably given to him upon the publication of his book, The Many Masks of Modern Art.
  Arrangement note
  The files are arranged by subject.
  - Biographical Data, circa 1983-2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 2005; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Awards, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Congratulatory Card, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1951-2011; 1920; Series 2; 0.75 Linear feet Box 1
  This series includes Theodore F. Wolff's correspondence with artists, editors, publishers, museums, and galleries. Subjects relate to Wolff's book projects, reviews, and other writings as well as his activities as an appraiser and fine arts consultant. Outgoing letters, mostly carbon copies, are to friends and family members and are of a personal nature. Types of correspondence include holiday cards, postcards and letters. Some of the letters are annotated and a small portion are illustrated by Wolff.
  Found is correspondence with his editors at The Christian Science Monitor Henrietta Buckmaster and Allan Bunce, printmakers, Norman and June Kraeft, and the writer, Tom Wolfe. The signficant portion of correspondence is with artists, including Richard Diebenkorn, Alexander Hogue,Ynez Johnston, Armin Landeck, Melissa Miller, Peter Milton, Robert Natkin, Theodoros Stamos, Clyfford Still, Athena Tachna, Stow Wengenroth, Jerome Witkin. Of interest, is Wolff's correspondence with Morris Graves and his partner, Robert Yarber. Graves's letters discuss his paintings, exhibitions, Wolff's writings as well as his thoughts on a variety of topics, aging, nature, technology, with allusions to Mayan, Chinese, and Hindu culture. Also found is a file of holograph letters from John Wilde.
  In general, letters are filed alphabetically by person or corporate name. Names with five or more letters are filed in their own folders. Wolff's outgoing letters are filed together in the first eleven folders.
  - Outgoing Letters (Carbon Copies), 1976-1993; 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5-15)
    (Includes a letter from John Taylor Arms)
  - Incoming Letters
    - A-C, 1990s-1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - D-F, 1977-2008 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      (Includes single letters from Enrico Donati and Helen Frankenthaler)
    - G-I, 1980s-2011 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - J-L, 1978-1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      (Includes a letter from Morton Kaish)
    - M-N, 1983-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - O-P, 1951; 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      (Includes a letter from Gordon Onslow-Ford)
    - R-S, 1968-1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      (Includes single letters from Norman Rockwell, John C. Swingdler, Victor Vasarely, and Robert Vickery)
    - T, 1981-1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - W, Z, 1975-2010 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      (Includes single letters from Marian Willard and Betsy Wyeth)
    - Graves, Morris, 1981-1999 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - Graves, Morris - Letters for a Book Proposal, circa 1932-circa 1997 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Wilde, John, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - First Names, 1983-1997; undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Loose Envelopes, 1976-1996 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Interviews, circa 1990-2002; Series 3; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  This series includes three interviews with Theodore Wolff and a panel discussion with Wolff and other artists, including Kim Emerson, Robert Erwin, and James Hubbell. Interviews with Enrico Donati and James Turrell were presumably used for source reference for Wolff's writings. Recordings are on five sound cassettes and three videocassettes.
  Interviews are arranged in chronological order.
  - Interview with James Turrell, circa 1990; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Discussion with Theodore F. Wolff and Other Artists (1992 April 26), 1 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Theodore F. Wolff Interview with Dan Erwine (1992 April 27), 1 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Interview with Enrico Donati, "Politics of Culture" (1998 October 20), 1 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Interview - "Degas with Theodore F. Wolff", 1998; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Interview with Theodore F. Wolff on "UO Today", 2002; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Writings, Talks, and Lectures, circa 1977-2005; Series 4; 2.8 Linear feet Boxes 2-4
  This series consists of photocopies and tearsheets of art columns that appeared in The Christian Science Monitor. Found are drafts and a set of tearsheets of articles numbered by Wolff for use in his book The Many Masks of Modern Art. Interspersed among the writings are clippings, letters, and lists. Two notebook binders, maintained by Wolff list the artists and topics that he wrote for The Monitor. Talks, lectures, and discussions on artists and art education are recorded on seven videocassettes and six sound cassettes.
  Writings are arranged by format and thereafter in chronological order.
  - Binder 1: Subject List of Articles and Reviews, circa 1977-circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Binder 2: Subject List of Articles and Reviews, circa 1977-circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Articles and Reviews, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9-14)
  - Articles and Reviews, 1982-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1-10)
  - Articles and Reviews in the International Edition of The Christian Science Monitor, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Drafts, The Many Masks of Modern Art, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Articles Used for The Many Masks of Modern Art
    - Tearsheets #1-#70, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
    - Tearsheets #134-#216, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - Tearsheets #72-#154, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Tearsheets #217-#247, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - One Set of Articles Used for The Many Masks of Modern Art, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Book, The Many Masks of Modern Art, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Draft, Discipline-Based Art Education: Becoming Students of Art (1985 November) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Wolff Talks on Willem de Kooning and "The Chicago Fifth Art Fair Exposition" (1984 May 18), 2 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Lecture, Tamarind Institute of Lithography, 1984; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Talk, "What is Unique About 20th Century Art" (1989 October 26), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Talk, "Refigured Painting" (1989 March 9), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Theodore F. Wolff Talks to Visual Arts Teachers Association (1989 October 26), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Threadevents Symposium, "Quilts and Art" (1991 January 23), 2 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Will Barnet and Theodore F. Wolff Talk at the National Academy of Design, 1993; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Talk at the Farnsworth Museum (1995 July 19), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lecture, "John Wilde: Master of Facts and Fancy" (1999 November 14), 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Theodore F. Wolff Discusses "Morris Graves: Longing and Reconciliation, Mystic Painters of the Northwest" (2002 April 11), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Talk, "The Creative Journey of Morris Graves: Clues from the Jordan Schnitzer Museum of Art Collection" (2005 April 8), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Subject Files, 1964-2004; circa 1940; Series 5; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 4-6
  Subject files document Wolff's professional interests, his writing projects, presentations, and talks. Letters, notes, annotated typescripts, tearsheets, agreements, press releases, printed material, clippings of reviews, exhibition catalogs, announcements, brochures, and photographs of artwork are found in varying combinations.
  Television interviews or documentaries on Joseph Solman, Enrico Donati, Esteban Vicente and a panel conference with Theodore F. Wolff at the Mid-Atlantic Fiber Association are recorded on four videocassettes.
  Files are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - "The Art of Joseph Solman", 1992; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Aspell, Peter, circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Barnet, Will, 1994-2000 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Birmelin, Robert, 1986; 1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Bloom, Hyman, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Book Proposal, Twentieth Century American Printmaking, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Brosen, Frederick, 1983-2000 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Curry, John Steuart, 1993-1998 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Documentary, "The Art & Vision of James Hubbell", 1989; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Donati, Enrico, 1982-2004 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Eastern Influences on Watercolor Painting, 1985; undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Esteban Vicente at 90", 1989; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Cards, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Frumkin/Adams Gallery, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "The Genius of Art", circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Goya, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Graves, Morris, 1982-2000 (Box 5, Folder 6-10)
  - Graves, Morris and Mark Tobey, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Henry Art Gallery, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Jessup, Robert, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Kaish, Morton, 1993-1996 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Kiefer, Anselm, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Kohlmeyer, Ida, 1983-1997 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Landscape, 1984-1999 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Laumier Park, circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Maury, Richard - Sherry French Gallery, 1986-1989 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Mabe, Manabu, 1987; 1983 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - MAFA Conference (2001 June), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Maine, 1991-2001 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Mangravite, Peppino, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Milton, Peter, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - The Monitor and the Arts, 1986-1990 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Natkin, Robert, 1981-2004 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - "The New York School: Four Decades"- Guggenheim Museum, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Peltenberg-Brechneff, Christian, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Print Show, 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - "Quality" - Jean Lipman, 1987-1990 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Quijada, Robert, 1983-1987 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Rickey, George, 1964-1997 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Santa Fe, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Speech in Boston - "Letter to a Reader Requesting a Precise Definition of Art", circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - "Spiritual Values in Contemporary Art", 1989 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Springville Museum of Art, 1990s (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Stamos, Theodoros, 1985-1990 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Tamarind Speech, "Print Connoisseurship in the Post-Modern Era", circa 1980-1990 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Tremain, Joyce, 1985-1997 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Turrell, James, 1981-1987 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Valpariso, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Warhol, Andy, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Weber, Idelle, 1982-1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Welz, Rebecca, 1991-2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Whitmore, Coby, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Whitaker, Frederic, circa 1940-2004 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Wilde, John, 1984-2004 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Witkin, Jerome, 1987-2003 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Wyeth, Andrew, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Printed Material, 1956-2006; Series 6; 2.2 Linear feet Boxes 6-8
  Found are books, exhibition catalogs, brochures, and journals that include Theodore F. Wolff's published reviews and essays on art and artists as well as his texts on the role of criticism in art education. Interspersed among the pages of the books are letters, clippings, and scattered printed material. A catalog of a Salvador Dalí exhibition is inscribed by the artist to Wolff.
  Files are arranged alphabetically by type of printed material.
  - Book, Enrico Donati: The Most Recent Work, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Book, Occluded Front: James Turrell, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Book, A Home Forum Reader, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Book, Morris Graves: Flower Paintings, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8.
  - Book, Joseph Solman, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Book, Enrico Donati: Surrealism & Beyond, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Book, Art Criticism and Education, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Book, Joyce Tremain, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Book, John Steuart Curry: Inventing the Middle West, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
  - Book, Wondrous Strange: The Wyeth Tradition, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Book, Wildeworld: The Art of John Wilde, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Book, Richard Kidwell Miller, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Book, The Watercolors of James Hubbell: Meditations on Nature and Life, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Brochures, 1987-2005 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Catalog, "Salvador Dalí" (1956 December 4-1957 January 5) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1983-2003 (Box 7, Folder 7-14)
  - Journals, 1976-2001 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Monograph, Drawings by Joseph Solman, 1925-1991, circa 1993 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Proceedings of an Interdisciplinary Symposium, Discipline in Art Education, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Oversized Book, Morris Graves: Flower Paintings, 1994 (Box 8)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 13.
  - Oversized Book, Joyce Tremain, 1997 (Box 8)
    Oversized material from Box 6, Folder 17.
- Artwork, 1942-1948; Series 7; 1 Folders Box 7
  Found here are seventeen sketches by Theodore F. Wolff, including several self-portraits.
  - Sketches, 1942-1948 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Photographs, circa 1980-circa 2011; Series 8; 0.25 Linear feet Box 7
  Included are portrait shots of Theodore F. Wolff, as well as photos of Wolff at an installation exhibition, in a classroom, and in his studio. Found are group photographs including two photographs of Wolff with Ida Kohlmeyer at an unidentified venue. There is a photograph of Wolff on an art critics' tour of Amsterdam. Most of the individuals are unidentified.
  - Theodore F. Wolff, circa 1980-circa 2011 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Theodore F. Wolff with Others, circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 20)